<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>New desktop setup</title>
  <slug>new-desktop-setup</slug>
  <author>Jan</author>
  <pubDate>2011-03-28 18:19:56</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2014-04-25 12:06:07</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;It’s been about 8 or 9 years since I’ve bought a new desktop system for myself. You can imagine the desktop I had was pretty antique and didn’t run the newest software quite well. Running Windows 7 on the &lt;a href="http://www.extremeoverclocking.com/reviews/processors/Intel_Pentium4_3.2C_1.html"&gt;Pentium 4 @ 3.2GHz&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="http://ixbtlabs.com/articles2/radeon/r9800xt.html"&gt;ATI Radeon 9800XT&lt;/a&gt; was a pain. Even running Windows XP SP3 was a starting to be a bit too much for the system.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Most of the time I’m buying a system I don’t need to upgrade too much in the future, perhaps some extra memory, but that’s about it. That’s why I needed to configure some high-end system which would be able to load a developer environment without much delay. Also running multiple VM’s is a requirement. Visual Studio requires quite some disk I/O, so an SSD is needed. VM’s can grow quite large, which means a second bulk storage disk has to be bought also. The more cores, the merrier. Lucky for me Intel had just released the &lt;a href="http://www.intel.com/technology/architecture-silicon/2ndgen/index.htm"&gt;Sandy Bridge&lt;/a&gt; architecture processors, which have 4 cores and Hyper Threading, resulting in 8 ‘cores’. An SB system should be compatible with 32GB of memory. At the moment RAM isn’t that expensive, but getting 32GB right from the start might be a bit overkill. I needed to save a bit of money for other parts, so I decided to go for 8GB for now. This means I can run 1 or 2 VM’s at the same time (depending on what’s running on them), which is good enough for now.&lt;br&gt;I’m a big fan of multiple monitors. For a developer, 2 monitors is the &lt;a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2008/03/does-more-than-one-monitor-improve-productivity.html"&gt;bare minimum&lt;/a&gt;. At work I always try to plug my laptop to a second (big) screen. Running with just 1 screen I feel crippled. At home I’ve got a single 24” monitor with a resolution of 1920x1200. It’s good, but it’s still 1 screen. AMD has this nice thing called &lt;a href="http://www.amd.com/US/PRODUCTS/TECHNOLOGIES/AMD-EYEFINITY-TECHNOLOGY/Pages/eyefinity.aspx"&gt;Eyefinity&lt;/a&gt;, which let’s you hook up to 6 monitors. For this to work I needed a graphics card which supported this. At the moment I don’t need to hook up 6 screens, but in the future I might just do that. For this to work you need 2 DisplayPort output connectors. Even though AMD says every HD6850 (and up) should/could support this, there’s awfully few who have implemented 2 of these ports. Lucky for me &lt;a href="http://www.sapphiretech.com/presentation/product/?leg=&amp;amp;psn=000101&amp;amp;pid=973"&gt;Sapphire&lt;/a&gt; has made a card which has 2 mini DP ports.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For all of these reasons I’ve chosen the following setup:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;- &lt;a href="http://ark.intel.com/Product.aspx?id=52213"&gt;Intel Core i7 2600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: The non-K version can’t be OC’ed, but has some extra virtualization features. Maybe usefull when running VM’s.&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.asus.com/product.aspx?P_ID=G1ixnvUxN70FJLbR"&gt;ASUS P8H67&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: I actually wanted the P8P67 (4x 6Gbps SATA), but that one costs a lot more, so this one will suffice&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.corsair.com/solid-state-drives/force-series/cssd-f120gb2-brkt.html"&gt;Corsair F120 SSD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: 120GB as a boot disk is large enough for me (now), also this disk is still produced with 34nm memory which doesn’t suffer the performance loss to the 25nm disks.&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.samsung.com/global/business/hdd/productmodel.do?group=&amp;amp;type=94&amp;amp;subtype=98&amp;amp;model_cd=560&amp;amp;ppmi=1219"&gt;Samsung Spinpoint F3 1TB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: Well, it’s a good disk and 1TB is good enough for a local disk as I still got a server with 8TB of storage&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.geil.com.tw/products/show/id/202"&gt;GeIL BlackDragon 8GB kit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: Cheapest memory I could find in the webshop&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.sapphiretech.com/presentation/product/?leg=&amp;amp;psn=000101&amp;amp;pid=973"&gt;Sapphire TOXIC HD 6850&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: The two mini-DP connectors for Eyefinity setup&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.coolermaster.com/product.php?product_id=6658"&gt;CoolerMaster Silent Pro Gold 700W&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: Has the gold label, so 90% efficient. Also the cheapest I could find with a gold label&lt;br&gt;- &lt;a href="http://www.antec.com/demo/ThreeHundred/"&gt;Antec Three Hundred&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reason: Antec has some very good cases. Every desktop I assembly will get an Antec case. They are a bit more expensive, but the quality is good.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After having had some problems with the hardware, I now run the full setup and it’s great! Boot time is under 15 seconds. VS2010 with ReSharper is faster as ever, installing and running software is a joy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Only thing missing is the Eyefinity setup. At the moment I still got 1 monitor, an &lt;a href="http://hardforum.com/showthread.php?t=1096025"&gt;Acer AL2423W&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a good enough screen, considering it’s age, but it’s 1 screen. I was hoping for a nice deal with several used monitors, but there aren’t many to my liking. For this reason I’ve bought 2 new &lt;a href="http://www.giga-zone.com/tw/products/features.php?prodNo=50050122"&gt;Gigazone Envision G2461w&lt;/a&gt; monitors. They are Edge-lit LED screens, which probably means the colors are a lot better compared to my old screen and use a lot less power. Hope they’ll arrive soon.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The only thing I need now is a VESA desk mount and attach all 3 monitors to them and pivot them, but that’s something for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories></categories>
  <comments></comments>
</post>