<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>Programmeer type</title>
  <slug>programmeer-type</slug>
  <author>Jan</author>
  <pubDate>2007-06-07 19:28:00</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2014-04-25 12:06:08</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;div class="ExternalClassE71982216BDF466EB8E6210F3AB7AB8E"&gt;Wat voor type programmeur/ontwikkelaar ben ik eigenlijk.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Aangezien ik een redelijk goede zelfkennis heb, weet ik dat natuurlijk wel. Het is natuurlijk nooit slecht om m'n zelfkennis ego te strelen met een test.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Wat blijkt, ik ben een &lt;strong&gt;DLSB&lt;/strong&gt; programmeur.&lt;br /&gt;Wat houdt dat nou in?&lt;br /&gt;Nou hier de uitleg:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're a Doer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You are very quick at getting tasks done. You believe the outcome is the most important part of a task and the faster you can reach that outcome the better. After all, time is money.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You like coding at a Low level.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You're from the old school of programming and believe that you should have an intimate relationship with the computer. You don't mind juggling registers around and spending hours getting a 5% performance increase in an algorithm.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You work best in a Solo situation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The best way to program is by yourself. There's no communication problems, you know every part of the code allowing you to write the best programs possible.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are a liBeral programmer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Programming is a complex task and you should use white space and comments as freely as possible to help simplify the task. We're not writing on paper anymore so we can take up as much room as we need.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Als je ook wilt weten wat voor programmeur je zelf bent.&lt;br /&gt;Klik hier: http://www.doolwind.com/index.php?page=11&lt;/div&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories></categories>
  <comments></comments>
</post>