<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<post>
  <title>Showing the ‘Recently Viewed’ books on your PRS-T1</title>
  <slug>showing-the-recently-viewed-books-on-your-prs-t1</slug>
  <author>Jan</author>
  <pubDate>2013-08-27 18:20:04</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2014-04-25 12:06:07</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;For some time now I&amp;rsquo;ve been in possession of the Sony PRS-T1 e-reader. E-readers are great devices and I find it much easier to read from an e-ink screen compared to a regular tablet screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there&amp;rsquo;s one thing which is really annoying specific to this Sony PRS-T1. It&amp;rsquo;s the home screen. Lucky for me the hardware runs on a modified Android OS, so there have been a lot of people modifying the looks and feels of the device. There&amp;rsquo;s a nice read of hacks and tweaks which can be found &lt;a href="http://wiki.mobileread.com/wiki/PRST1_Rooting_and_Tweaks"&gt;on this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the tweaks which can be found over there is changing the behavior of the &amp;lsquo;Recently Added&amp;rsquo; pane on the home screen. If you read a couple of books at the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s better to see the &amp;lsquo;Recently Viewed&amp;rsquo; books on the home screen. That way it&amp;rsquo;s possible to quickly navigate to the books you are reading.&lt;br /&gt;To change this behavior you need to access one of the databases on the device and create a new trigger in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The databases on the device are (similar?) to &lt;a href="http://www.sqlite.org/"&gt;SQLite&lt;/a&gt; databases, therefore you can connect to them using the &lt;a href="http://sqliteadmin.orbmu2k.de/"&gt;SQLite Administrator&lt;/a&gt;. After having installed this tool you can just open the books database on the device:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://jan-v.nl/Media/Default/WindowsLiveWriter/ShowingtheRecentlyViewedbooksonyourPRST1_11CE3/image_2.png"&gt;&lt;img title="image" style="display: inline; border-width: 0px;" border="0" alt="image" src="http://jan-v.nl/Media/Default/WindowsLiveWriter/ShowingtheRecentlyViewedbooksonyourPRST1_11CE3/image_thumb.png" width="575" height="428" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run the following query on the database:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="brush:sql"&gt;CREATE TRIGGER recently_opened_trigger AFTER UPDATE OF reading_time ON books
BEGIN
   UPDATE books SET added_date = 0 WHERE _id = new._id;
   UPDATE books SET added_date = reading_time WHERE reading_time NOT NULL AND _id &amp;lt;&amp;gt; new._id;
END
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a trigger which updates the books&amp;rsquo; added date to the last date you&amp;rsquo;ve read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve tested this on the &lt;a href="http://www.sony.nl/support/nl/product/PRS-T1/downloads/PRST1_FW_PC_v1005_11130"&gt;latest firmware&lt;/a&gt; (1.0.05.11130, issued on 26/11/2012) and this still works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: If the above method damages your device, I can not be held responsible. Executing these modifications is at your own risk!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s not a lot of other stuff you can do in these databases, but if you want to root your device, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to run apps on it as well. I&amp;rsquo;m not really into that, so won&amp;rsquo;t try it out in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories></categories>
  <comments></comments>
</post>